Guide to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) records, 1918-2020, bulk 1970-2020 RL.01304
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Program and Subject Files, 1979-2015
  - ICTJ Conferences/Workshops, 1997-2015
    - Conferences: Audiovisual Materials
      - "The Big Deal": A Conference on Police/Youth Empowerment, 2000; VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0069)
    - ICTJ Workshops and Conferences Electronic Records, 254 digital files; approximately 29.5 gigabytes.
      Bahrain Truth Seeking Workshop, book launches for "Justice as Prevention" and "What Happened to the Women," Transitional Justice Essentials Course in New York 2009, Gender and Transitional Justice in Africa conference, Nuremberg Conference
- Administrative Records, 1973-2020
  The Administrative Records series contains presidential files, logistical files from the organization's operation, and individual staff files. The latter group represents the records of 16 prominent ICTJ staff members; former presidents and co-founders, program directors and prosecution unit leaders. Formats in these records include office files, notebooks, printed materials such as publicity, articles, and publicastions, and audiovisual recordings.
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of user copies.
  Electronic files may only be accessed in the Rubenstein Library reading room. Contact Research Services in advance to request access to these files.
  - Staff Files, 1973-2013
    Contains the files of 16 ICTJ high-level staff members arranged alphabetically by last name. Includes the files of co-founders Alex Boraine, Priscilla Hayner, and Paul van Zyl, as well as long-standing criminal justice director Marieke Wierda and prosecutions director Vasuki Nesiah, and Louis Bickford, a multi-unit director. Most of the staff files include audiovisual components, including videos and sound recordings. These may require the production of listening or viewing copies.
    The staff files narrate the story of ICTJ from its initial creation to its development into a strong, influential, global leader in transitional justice.
    Arranged alphabetically by last name.
    - ICTJ Staff Diagram, 2001; 1 folders (Box 48)
    - Louis Bickford, 1995-2010; 5 Linear Feet 9 boxes
      The Louis Bickford papers house materials grouped into these categories: Administrative, Geographic Regions, Print Materials, and Professional Papers.
      Biographical
      Louis Bickford joined the International Center for Transitional Justice at its foundation in 2001. During his time at the ICTJ, Bickford served as Director of the Memory and Memorials Unit as well as the Policymakers and Civil Society Unit.
      - Professional Files, 2000-2007; 9 folders (Box 154, Box 155)
        Includes Louis Bickford's notes, notebooks, calendars, incoming and outgoing correspondence, articles, conference presentations, drafts, a book proposal, financial documents, and International Center for Transitional Justice onboarding materials.
      - Administrative, 1997-2010; 49 folders (Box 147, Box 148, Box 149, Box 150)
        Materials include International Center for Transitional Justice budgets, work plans, ICTJ units and working groups, fellowship programs, staff retreats, meetings, organization charts, office floorplans, Board of Directors meetings, strategic planning, background on the ICTJ, conferences, summer institutes, workshops, various conference agendas and programs, contracts, courses, job descriptions, correspondence, and essays and research on transitional justice, truth commissions, constitutional and international law, and lustration. Files are arranged in original order; budget files are in chronological order.
      - Geographic Regions, 1998-2010; 30 folders (Box 151, Box 152, Box 153)
        Includes materials on African NGOs, Argentina, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Burma, Canada, Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Czech Republic, Guantánamo, Guatemala, Israel and Palestine, Japan, Mexico, Northern Ireland, Perú, Serbia, Srebrenica and Sarajevo, Uganda, Uruguay, and Zimbabwe. Country files contain journal articles and other publications, including ICTJ reports, related to governance, rule of law, political stability, truth and reconciliation, reparations, and human rights violations.
        Files are arranged alphabetically by country. Materials are chiefly in English, but these records do contain some materials in Spanish and French.
      - Print Materials, 2001-2009; 5 folders (Box 153, Box 154)
        Materials include International Center for Transitional Justice pamphlets, annual reports, occasional justice series, gender justice series, and posters for an ICTJ Transitional Justice Essentials Course.
    - Louis Bickford: Audiovisual Materials
      - Louis Bickford, VHS (Box 128, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0195)
      - Louis Bickford on Public Memorials, 2008-08-13; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0076)
        Virtual Instructor Project
    - Alexander Boraine, 2003; 3 folders (Box 48, Box 145)
      Transitional Justice course materials. Correspondence re: honorary degree from Linfield College.
    - Alexander Boraine: Audiovisual Materials
      - Alex Boraine Interview, 2003-06-16; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0039)
      - Alex Boraine SABC TV, 2004 April; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0008)
      - BBC Newshour Interview, 2003-06-15; Cassette (Box 134, Audio-cassette RL01304-CS-0035)
      - BBC Newshour Interview, 2003-12-10; Cassette (Box 135, Audio-cassette RL01304-CS-0045)
      - Boraine in Sierra Leone, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0040)
      - Boraine in Sierra Leone, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0041)
      - Boraine in Sierra Leone, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0042)
      - Newsworld Today, 2003-07-15; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0147)
      - South Africa/Nigeria, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0038)
      - Visit of Dr. Alex Boraine ICTJ President to the Truth and Reconciliation Commission in Sierra Leone, 2003-03-27/2003-03-31; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0151)
    - Christina Correa: Audiovisual Materials
      - Christina Correa on Reparations for Victims, 2008-09-11; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0077)
    - Eric Darko, 1997-2005; 2 folders (Box 48)
      Materials on Cuba, various country publications.
      - Eric Darko files
    - Eric Darko: Audiovisual Materials
      - University of Queensland Master of Philosophy "Transitional Justice and South Africa", 2006; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0129)
    - Pablo de Greiff: Audiovisual Materials
      - Pablo de Greiff interview with CBC Radio One, 2004-12-08; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0005)
        Interview about reparations
    - Mark Freeman: Audiovisual Materials
      - CBC News: Today Mark Freeman Interview, 2011-05-07; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0148)
    - Eduardo Gonzalez: Audiovisual Materials
      - Eduardo Gonzalez on Public Hearings/Perú, 2008-09-11; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0078)
    - Elizabeth Goodfriend, 2006-2008; 14 folders (Box 48)
      Research Unit meeting notes, Liberia Working Group and Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Liberia work plans, budgets, goals, meeting agendas and news reports, International Policy Unit notes on Liberia.
    - Elizabeth Goodfriend Posters, 2008; 1 folders (Oversize-folder 2)
      Posters of "Sierrarat" TRC, Open Society Initiative of West Africa and Transitional Justice Working Group TRC posters, wanted poster for Jose Efrain Rios Montt.
    - Blaz Gutierrez, 1997-2008; 38 folders (Box 49)
      ICTJ mission statement, academic articles on transitional justice, human rights, and truth seeking, UN Inter-Agency Disarmament, Demobilization, and Reintegration Working Group, ICTJ staff retreat, ICTJ workplan and summary, UN panel on ICC, country files.
    - Blaz Gutierrez: Audiovisual Materials
      - Coordinadora nacional de Derechos Humanos: Documentos Básicos, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0145)
        Peru
      - Coordinadora nacional de Derechos Humanos: Investigación Forense y Derechos Humanos, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0147)
      - Coordinadora nacional de Derechos Humanos: Jurisprudencia para la Judicialización, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0146)
      - Instituto Interamericano de Derechos Humanos "Verdad, justicia y reparación", CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0133)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0134)
        11 discs
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0135)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0136)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0137)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0138)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0139)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0140)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0141)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0142)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0143)
      - International and Local Lessons in Truth Seeking (Greensboro Truth Commission), 2006-07-08; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0144)
      - International Seminar on Justice and Reparations for victims of sexual violence in contexts of armed conflict, 2006-08-09/2006-08-10; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0130)
      - International Seminar Y que fue de las mujeres?, 2007-03-27/2007-03-28; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0132)
      - Peace Song of the Liberia TRC, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0131)
    - Priscilla Hayner, 1989-2007
      - Priscilla Hayner: Country Files, 1989-2007; 196 folders (Box 49-54)
        Countries of note include Afghanistan, Ghana, Liberia, Peru, Sierra Leone, and Zimbabwe.
        Country files A-B in box 49, Burundi-I in box 50, K-M in box 51, N-Sierra Leone in box 52, Sierra Leone-United States in box 53, and United States-Z in box 54.
      - Priscilla Hayner: Establishment of ICTJ, 1989-2002; 28 folders (Box 54-55)
        Contains early documents related to the founding and funding of ICTJ and ICTJ programs. Includes staff diagram, fundraising information, grants, project descriptions, architecture diagrams.
      - Priscilla Hayner: Conferences, Workshops, Invitations, Speaking Events, and Trips, 2000-2007; 144 folders (Box 55-57)
        All conferences, workshops, speaking or event invitations, and trips by Priscilla Hayner.
      - Priscilla Hayner: Staff Development, 2002-2007; 65 folders (Box 58-59)
        Knowledge management recommendations, management meetings, all unit meetings, ICTJ staff newsletter, ICTJ board meetings, Truth Commissions Affinity group meetings, Transitional Justice Alliance meetings, organizational review, staff retreats, workplans, fundraising.
      - Priscilla Hayner: Program and Thematic Files, 2000-2005; 72 folders (Box 59-60)
        NYU Truth Commissions project, Policymakers program, Red Cross program on the missing, ICTJ Fellows program, NYU Lessons Learned project, intelligence oversight project, grant proposals, project research, UN Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights Toolkit project, apologies, capacity building, Chicago Principles of Post-Conflict Justice, ICC, memorials and memory work, UN rule of law report.
      - Priscilla Hayner: Writings and Contributions, 2001-2007; 56 folders (Box 60-61)
        Interviews, media and radio appearances, publications,Occasional Paper (O&A) series of edits and submissions, work on Unspeakable Truth book project.
    - Priscilla Hayner: Audiovisual Materials
      - Legacy of Hope Foundation, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0040)
      - Legacy of Hope Foundation: Our Stories Our Strength", 2007; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0041)
      - Songs from the Indian Residential School Legacy, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0042)
      - Where are the Children? Healing the Legacy of the Residential Schools, 2002; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0043)
      - "Global Journalism", 2005-01-20; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0010)
        Interview about Auschwitz
      - Buru Island Tapol #1, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0044)
      - Massaker, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0045)
      - Weekend Edition Sunday Interview, 2001-08-25; Cassette (Box 135, Audio-cassette RL01304-CS-0044)
    - Lisa Magarrell, 1992-2010
      - Lisa Magarrell: Country Files, 1992-2010; 62 folders (Box 62-63)
        Countries of note include Argentina, Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Ghana, Japan, Kyrgyzstan, Peru South Africa, and the United States.
      - Lisa Magarrell: Conferences and Workshops, 2003-2007; 6 folders (Box 63)
        Historical Justice in International Perspectives Conference, Second Annual Human Rights Conference, conference in Accura, Ghana.
      - Lisa Magarrell: Staff Development, 2004-2010; 4 folders (Box 63)
        ICTJ GTRC workshop, assessment of current work, ICTJ workplan, Asia Regional Training, ICTJ Donor Consortium.
      - Lisa Magarrell: Program and Thematic Files, 1998-2010; 44 folders (Box 64-65)
        Long Term Legacies (LTL) project, Open Society Institute (OSI) project on US accountability, gender and transitional justice, disappearances, reconciliation, reparations, truth commissions, vetting, ICC, Due Process of Law Foundation books.
    - Ian Martin, 1986-2005; 33 folders (Box 66)
      Fund for Peace report, Conciliation Resources Accord, articles about amnesty and peace agreements, country files including Sudan/Darfur, East Timor, Ethiopia, Israel/Palestine, Northern Ireland, Papua New Guinea, Philippines, Solomon Islands, and UN Guidelines for representatives in negotiations of conflict resolution.
    - Ian Martin: Audiovisual Materials
      - BBC Newshour Interview, 2003-05-22; Cassette (Box 135, Audio-cassette RL01304-CS-0046)
      - Ian Martin C3C IV, VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0152)
      - Ian Martin Interview, 2003-01-10; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0154)
      - Ian Martin Live Interview, VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0153)
      - Ian's CNN Jakarta Trials Interview, VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0149)
    - Alexander Mayer-Rieckh: Audiovisual Materials
      - ICTJ 1 Program, 2008-07-29; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0125)
      - ICTJ 2 Country, 2008-07-29; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0126)
      - ICTJ 3 Research, 2008-07-29; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0127)
      - ICTJ 4 Training and Advocacy, ICTJ general, and general docs, 2008-07-29; CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0128)
    - Juan Méndez, 2007-2008; 14 folders (Box 67)
      Conferences and papers on genocide, ICTJ comments on Truth, Justice and Reconciliation bills, articles and newspaper clippings about Brazil, e-mails, published materials in Spanish, APRODEH information about Fujimori penal trial.
    - Juan Méndez: Audiovisual Materials
      - Hardtalk, 2005-01-26; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0145)
        BBC Post Production
      - Interview with Juan Mendez for Communications, 2007-05-22; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0129)
    - Kelli Muddell, 2001-2006; 1 folders (Box 67)
      Special Court for Sierra Leone materials.
    - Habib Nassar, 2005-2012; 19 folders (Box 67-68)
      Country files including Iraq, Lebanon, Morocco, and Tunisia; draft work plans, disappearances and missing persons across the Middle East, reparations reports. In Arabic.
    - Vasuki Nesia, 1990-2007
      - Vasuki Nesiah: Country Files, 1990-2006; 209 folders (Box 68-72)
        Countries of note include Afghanistan, Ghana, Sri Lanka, Sierra Leone, South Africa, and Zimbabwe.
        Country files A-Ghana in box 68, Ghana-Peru in box 69, Philippines-South Africa in box 70, South Africa-Sri Lanka in box 71, Sri Lanka-Z in box 72.
      - Vasuki Nesiah: Conferences and Workshops, 2001-2005; 12 folders (Box 72-73)
        Women's Caucus for Gender Justice, conferences on conflict and transitional justice, accountability for past human rights violations, disappearances and transitional justice training, Asia Society symposium, International Center for Tolerance Education conference, World Conference against Racism.
      - Vasuki Nesiah: Staff Development, 2001-2007; 27 folders (Box 73-74)
        ICTJ internal documents, discussions and comment on Ghana TRC, reparations for violations of human rights and peacebuilding in South Asia, ICTJ Gender Program discussions, Country Programs Unit Committee documents.
      - Vasuki Nesia: Writings, 2001-2004; 17 folders (Box 74)
        Morocco's claim's to western Sahara, truth commission writings, unofficial truth projects summary, intelligence oversight project, "The Ground Beneath Her Feet," international law, and public international law.
      - Vasuki Nesia: Program and Thematic Files, 1996-2006; 72 folders (Box 74-77)
        International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) project on the missing, UN University project, UN documents on human rights, thematic files including amnesty, children and human rights, corruption, elections, gender and truth commissions, gender and transitional justice, ICC, memorials, legal accountability, reparations, relationships between truth commissions and NGOs, truth seeking, and women in conflict.
    - Joanna Rice, 2006-2013; 9 folders (Box 77)
      Introduction to ICTJ's Truth and Memory Program, workplan, ICTJ style guide, memorialization and democracy, memory and justice articles, Balkans Truth Commission.
    - Miranda Sissons, 2007-2009; 11 folders (Box 77)
      Research resources, transitions working group, knowledge management working group, notes and project files, ICTJ Design, Monitoring, and Evaluation group, ICTJ research unit and calendar.
    - Sandra Spady, 2008-2011; 7 folders (Box 77)
      Indigenous peoples conference, western Balkans materials, political and security developments in Kenya, knowledge management.
    - Paul van Zyl, 2003-2005; 2 folders (Box 78)
      see Alex Boraine.
    - Paul van Zyl: Audiovisual Materials
      - CNN 1 Q&A, 2003-12-08; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0146)
      - Fresh Air Interview, 2001-12-03; Cassette (Box 135, Audio-cassette RL01304-CS-0043)
      - PVZ on CNN Domestic, 2004-07-01; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0143)
    - Paul van Zyl Electronic Records, 10 audiovisual (Windows Media format) and document (Microsoft Word format) files; approximately 0.48 GB (Digital-materials RL01304-SET-0007)
      Files related to van Zyl's TEDGlobal Africa talk.
    - Marieke Wierda, 1973-2007
      - Marieke Wierda: Country Files, 1994-2006; 109 folders (Box 78-82)
        Countries of note include Afghanistan, Peru, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Sudan, and Yugoslavia.
        Afghanistan in boxes 78-80, countries B-J in box 80, P-Sudan in box 81, Sudan-Z in box 82
      - Marieke Wierda: Conferences and Workshops, 2001-2007; 38 folders (Box 82-83)
        World Bank Symposium, Vancouver Dialogues, transitional justice conferences, seminars and events on international law, International Criminal Law in the Arab World conference, UNHCHR workshops, ICTJ conferences, Asia Society Symposium, Victims Rights Working Group meetings.
      - Marieke Wierda: Program and Thematic Files, 1973-2007; 65 folders (Box 83-85)
        Prosecutions, rule of law and transitional justice, Judicial Supplements, UN documents, ICC Trust Fund for Victims, international criminal tribunals, intelligence oversight, UN Security Council reports, Inter-American Court of Human Rights reports, victim participation in prosecutions.
      - Marieke Wierda: Staff Development, 2001-2007; 19 folders (Box 85)
        Staff retreats, ICTJ board meetings, policy unit meetings, ICTJ program staff, prosecutions workplan.
      - Marieke Wierda: Writings, 2002; 2 folders (Box 85)
        "Procedural Developments in International Criminal Courts," book review.
    - Marieke Wierda: Audiovisual Materials
      - BBC Newshour Interview, 2004-03-10; Cassette (Box 135, Audio-cassette RL01304-CS-0047)
    - Nisma Zaman, 2006-2007; 4 folders (Box 143)
      4 spiral notebooks.
  - Institutional Memory/President's Files, 1990-2014
    The files of ICTJ former presidents Juan Mendez and Alex Boraine. Alex Boraine was a co-founder of ICTJ and served as its president from 2001-2003. Juan Mendez served as the president from 2004-2009. Their work within ICTJ spans topics from the founding of ICTJ to truth commissions to NGO partnerships to transitional justice and human rights issues throughout the world. Their work brought them to many conferences, symposia, trainings, and speaking engagements and allowed them to publish numerous writings for more than a decade with ICTJ. This series is comprised of name files, organization files, conferences and events, transitional justice and human rights issues, ICTJ management, correspondence, and writings/publications.
    Name files arranged alphabetically by last name, organization files arranged alphabetically by organization, and conferences and events arranged chronologically.
    - Name Files, 2000-2008; 18 folders (Box 108)
      Individuals who worked with ICTJ.
    - Organization Files, 1997-2009; 54 folders (Box 108-109)
      Organizations that worked with ICTJ.
      Arranged alphabetically by organization title.
    - Organization Files: Audiovisual Materials
      - Abduction, VHS (Box 128, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0194)
        B92 Belgrade project
      - UNESCO Memory of the World: Documentary Heritage of the Peoples of the World, CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0084)
    - Conferences and Events, 1999-2008; 27 folders (Box 109)
      Conferences, events, workshops, and symposia attended by senior leaders at ICTJ.
    - Truth Commissions, 1990-2008; 22 folders (Box 109-110)
      Contains files from truth commissions attended, directed, and assisted by ICTJ senior leaders.
      Arranged alphabetically by country.
    - Transitional Justice and Human Rights, 2000-2013; 28 folders (Box 110-111)
      Includes projects by Alex Boraine and Juan Mendez about transitional justice, human rights, domestic prosecutions, capacity building, restorative justice, institutional reform, reparations, amnesty, and redress.
    - ICTJ Management, 2000-2014; 22 folders (Box 111)
      Materials related to the founding and running of ICTJ. Includes ICTJ concept papers, media, outreach, and communications, criteria for ICTJ involvement, ICTJ high level meetings, management meetings, ICTJ partnerships, ICTJ thematic plans, proposals for retreats, program units, and committee meetings.
    - Writings and Publications, 2000-2008; 14 folders (Box 111)
      Includes writings, publications, and editorial notes from Juan Mendez and Alex Boraine.
    - Correspondence, 2001-2006; 6 folders (Box 112)
      Correspondence, e-mails, memos, outlines, and proposals between senior level staff at ICTJ.
  - Administrative Files, 1997-2020